<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CoLoMoTo model collection on CoLoMoTo notebooks</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/</link><description>Recent content in CoLoMoTo model collection on CoLoMoTo notebooks</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Contribution of ROS and metabolic status to neonatal and adult CD8+ T cell activation</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2019-mammal-neonatal-tcell-metabolism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2019-mammal-neonatal-tcell-metabolism/</guid><description>The low response to infection in neonatal T cells contributes to a high incidence of morbidity and mortality. Here we evaluated the effect of the cytoplasmic and mitochondrial levels of Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) of neonatal CD8+T cells on their low activation. This model captures the interplay between antigen recognition with ROS and metabolic status in T cell responses. This model displays alternative stable states, which corresponds to different cell fates, i.</description></item><item><title>Control of Th1/Th2/Th17/Treg/Tfh/Th9/Th22 cell differentiation</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2014-mammal-th-differentiation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2014-mammal-th-differentiation/</guid><description>Logical modeling has proven suitable for the dynamical analysis of large signaling and transcriptional regulatory networks. In this context, signaling input components are generally meant to convey external stimuli, or environmental cues. In response to such external signals, cells acquire specific gene expression patterns modeled in terms of attractors (e.g. stable states). The capacity for cells to alter or reprogram their differentiated states upon changes in environmental conditions is referred to as cell plasticity.</description></item><item><title>Logical model of the regulatory network controlling dorsal-ventral axis specification in the sea urchin P. lividius</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2020-seaurchin-dv-axis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2020-seaurchin-dv-axis/</guid><description>We have integrated novel experimental results with previous data about the roles of Nodal and BMP pathways in early development of Paracentrotus lividus in the form of a regulatory graph, which was complemented with logical rules, thereby enabling the simulation of cell responses to varying signalling inputs along the dorsal-ventral axis. This logical model was then extended to account for ligand diffusion and enable multicellular simulations, which accurately recapitulated gene expression in wild type embryos, accounting for the specification of the three main ectodermal regions, namely ventral ectoderm, ciliary band and dorsal ectoderm, and further recapitulated sophisticated mutant phenotypes.</description></item><item><title>Lysis vs lysogeny decision in the phage lambda</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/1995-lambda-lysis-lysogeny/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/1995-lambda-lysis-lysogeny/</guid><description>A number of bacterial and viral genes take part in the decision between lysis and lysogenisation in temperate bacteriophages. In the case of the bacteriophage lambda, at least 5 viral regulatory products (CI, Cro, CII, N and CIII) and several bacterial genes are involved (see [1] for an excellent overview).
For the sake of explanation clarity, we proceed in two steps. We present a model of the core of the lambda regulatory network, constituted by the cross-regulation between the regulatory genes CI (encoding the repressor) and Cro (see phage2.</description></item><item><title>Multilevel mammalian cell cycle model</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2016-mammal-cell-cycle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2016-mammal-cell-cycle/</guid><description>This model is an extension of the seminal model of the G1/S restriction point control of mammalian cell cycle, published by Fauré et al [1] . We used model-checking and computing tree logics (CTL) to progressively refine Fauré&amp;rsquo;s model in order to fit recent experimental observations. The resulting model accounts for the sequential activation of cyclins, the role of Skp2, and emphasizes a multifunctional role for the cell cycle inhibitor Rb.</description></item><item><title>Restriction point control of the mammalian cell cycle</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2006-mammal-cell-cycle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2006-mammal-cell-cycle/</guid><description>On the basis of a previous modelling study by Novak and Tyson [1] , we have recently proposed a generic Boolean model of the core network controlling the restriction point of the mammalian cell cycle.
For proper logical parameter values, the simulation of this Boolean model leads to dynamical behaviours (sequences of activations and inactivations of key regulatory products) in qualitative agreement with current experimental data.
However, as kinetic details are still lacking, many different (in)activation pathways are compatible with existing data, including fully synchronous transition pathways.</description></item><item><title>T cells response to CTLA4 and PD-1 checkpoint inhibitors</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2020-mammal-tcell-checkpoint-inhibitors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2020-mammal-tcell-checkpoint-inhibitors/</guid><description>This comprehensive model integrates the available data on T cell activation, taking into account CTLA4 and PD-1 checkpoint inhibitory pathways. It encompasses 216 components and 451 regulatory arcs.
To ease the verification of the behaviour of this large logical model, we have designed a modular approach based on a unit testing framework used in software development. Furthermore, to compare the respective impact of the activation of the two checkpoints, we have designed a value propagation technique enabling the analytical computation of all the nodes frozen following the persisting activation or inhibition of any model component.</description></item><item><title>T-lymphocyte specification</title><link>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2019-mammal-tcell-specification/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aurelien-naldi.github.io/notebooks/models/2019-mammal-tcell-specification/</guid><description>We have applied the logical modelling framework to the regulatory network controlling T-lymphocyte specification. This process involves cross- regulations between specific T-cell regulatory factors with factors driving alternative differentiation pathways, which remain accessible during the early steps of thymocyte development. Many transcription factors needed for T-cell specification are required in other hematopoietic differentiation pathways, and are combined in a fine-tuned, time-dependent fashion to achieve T-cell commitment.
Using the software GINsim, we integrated current knowledge into a dynamical model, which recapitulates the main developmental steps from early progenitors entering the thymus up to T-cell commitment, as well as the impact of various documented environmental and genetic perturbations.</description></item></channel></rss>